Guide to the Edwin J. Beinecke Collection of Robert Louis Stevenson
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Manuscripts, 1828-1960; Series II; 13.35; (34 boxes)
  In this collection, a significant number of manuscript items are bound with others. In these cases, references to physical locations are provided in folder notes. The arrangement of loose manuscript items, such as drafts of different poems on the recto and verso of a single sheet, has been preserved and, here too, references to physical locations are provided in folder notes.
  Volume five of McKay's Catalogue also describes manuscripts found in correspondence and printed materials. References to manuscripts located in Series I. Correspondence are provided in the list below. References to presentation inscriptions in printed materials, however, have not been preserved in this guide; manuscript notes and inscriptions are commonly documented in the catalog records in Orbis.
  Manuscripts by Others consists of writings by family members, writings by others about Stevenson, and documents relating to Stevenson. Writings by family members features the diaries of Margaret Isabella Stevenson, in forty-seven volumes dating from 1853 to 1897, and various works, as well as notebooks, by Thomas Stevenson. Writings by others consists chiefly of reflections on Stevenson and his work. Documents include legal and financial records, such as wills, conveyances, and royalty statements.
  - Manuscripts by Robert Louis Stevenson
    Manuscripts by Robert Louis Stevenson is arranged alphabetically by title (italicized or in quotes), first line (bracketed and in quotes), or supplied title (bracketed).
    - "In Abererch" (5929), undated (Box 24, Folder 583)
    - ["About the world with bag on back..."] (5933), undated
    - [Accounts] (5935), [1880] (Box 24, Folder 584)
    - "Ad Se Ipsum" (5939), 1895 May 19
    - [Address to Students at Malua Institution, Upolu, Samoa] (5940), [1889?] (Box 24, Folder 585)
    - [Address to the Samoan Chiefs] (5941-5942), 1894 October, undated (Box 24, Folder 586-587)
    - ["Adorner of the uncomely, wake"] (5946), undated (Box 24, Folder 588)
    - "Alcaics to Horatio F. Brown" (5950), 1881 (Box 24, Folder 589)
    - ["All night through, raves or broods..."] (5953), [1876 March?]
    - "All Things on Earth and Sea," poem (3271), [1873?]
    - "Alpine Diversions," article (copy) (5955), [1881?] (Box 24, Folder 590)
    - The Amateur Emigrant (5956), undated (Box 24, Folder 591)
    - "American Pirates Trades Union" (5957), [circa 1885] (Box 24, Folder 592)
    - "American Rights and Wrongs" (5958), undated (Box 24, Folder 593)
    - [Anagrams on Town in Asia] (5959), 1865 June 5
    - ["And I seem to myself forever..."] (5961), undated
    - ["And still on that desired [?] scene..."] (5963), undated
    - ["And still to follow after hope..."] (3153), [1879?]
    - "Anecdote of a Sermon" (5965), 1865 June 5
    - ["Anon under the tropic sun..."] (5966), undated (Box 24, Folder 594)
    - "Another [Song]" (5967), undated
    - [Anstruther, Notes From, Etc.] (5969), undated
    - "The Antiquities of Midlothian," notes (5970), [1861?] (Box 24, Folder 595)
    - [Archerfield, Francis and Fred], "Chapter II" (5973), undated
    - ["As Daniel, bird-alone in that far land..."] (2646 and 5975-5976), 1872
    - ["As in the hostel by the bridge, I sate..."], poem (5978), 1872
    - ["As one who having wandered all night long..."], poem (5982), 1878 April
    - ["As starts the absent dreamer, when a train..."], poem (5984), 1872
    - ["As when a galleon in the height of noon..."], poem (5986), undated
    - "Assasinat Par Amour," article (5987), undated (Box 24, Folder 596)
    - "Audawcious Odyshes," poem (5992-5993), undated (Box 24, Folder 597)
    - "Authors and Publishers" (5997), [circa 1890-1891] (Box 25, Folder 598)
    - "Autobiographical Notes" (5998), [1887?] (Box 25, Folder 599)
    - "Autumn," poem (3553), 1868 December 10
    - ["Aye sure, the ways are steep, the drifting snow..."], poem (6001), undated (Box 25, Folder 600)
    - "The Barbizon Free-Trading Company, Unlimited" (6002), undated (Box 25, Folder 601-602)
    - "The Baron of Manaheit," poem (6003), [1864-1865] (Box 25, Folder 603)
    - "The Bass Rock," table of contents (6004), undated
    - ["Be the glory and the dream..."], poem (6005), [1884] (Box 25, Folder 604)
    - ["Behold as goblins dark of mein..."], poem (6008), undated (Box 25, Folder 605)
    - "The Bells of a Summer Sunday," poem (6011), undated
    - [Béranger, Pierre Jean de], notes (6012), undated (Box 25, Folder 606)
    - [Béranger, Pierre Jean de], article (6013), undated (Box 25, Folder 607-608)
    - "The Best Thing in Edinburgh," speech (6015), 1876 (Box 26, Folder 609)
    - ["Between white hawthorn hedges..."], poem (6016), undated (Box 26, Folder 610)
    - The Black Arrow, table of contents (6018), undated (Box 26, Folder 611)
    - "The Blast--1875," poem (6019), 1875 July
    - "The Body Snatcher" (6020), undated
    - "Bough R.S.A., Samuel," obituary (6021), [1878?] (Box 26, Folder 612)
    - [Brashiana 1-17] (6024-6048), [1882], undated
    - "Bright is the Ring of Words," song lyrics (6051-6053), undated (Box 26, Folder 613)
    - "The Builder's Doom," poem (6057), undated (Box 26, Folder 614)
    - ["By dim recess and dripping weir..."], poem (6060), undated
    - "The Canoe Speaks" (6065, 6067-6069), undated (Box 26, Folder 615)
    - [Casco (Yacht)], agreement (6071), 1888 June 21 (Box 26, Folder 616)
    - "The Castaways of Soledad" (6072), undated (Box 26, Folder 617)
    - "Catologus Librorum Carissimorum" (6073), undated (Box 26, Folder 618)
    - Catriona (6074-6075 and 6077-6085), undated (Box 26, Folder 619-629)
    - "The Catspaw," table of contents (6086), undated
    - [Basil Champney. "A Quiet Corner of England"], review (6088), undated (Box 26, Folder 630)
    - The Charity Bazaar, dialogue (6091), undated (Box 27, Folder 631)
    - [Charles VI, King of France], notes (6092), undated (Box 27, Folder 632)
    - [Charles VII, King of France], notes (6093), undated (Box 27, Folder 633)
    - [Charles IX, King of France], notes (6094), undated (Box 27, Folder 634)
    - [Charles of Orleans], notes (6095), undated (Box 27, Folder 635)
    - [Checks] (8328-8329), 1887 August 18 (Box 27, Folder 636)
    - [Chess Game], notes (6096), undated (Box 27, Folder 637)
    - [Children], notes (6097), undated (Box 27, Folder 638)
    - [Civilization, Law, Public Sentiment, Etc.], notes (6098), undated (Box 27, Folder 639)
    - ["Clearly--I'll go straight t'the Bible..."], poem (6100), 1871, undated
    - ["Climb up with me among the hay..."] (6101), undated
    - "The Clockmaker" (6102), undated (Box 27, Folder 640)
    - [Cockermouth and Keswick], essay (6103), [1871?] (Box 27, Folder 641)
    - ["The cock's clear voice into the clearer air..."], poem (6104), 1879 (Box 27, Folder 642)
    - [College for Men and Women] (6105), 1874 (Box 27, Folder 643)
    - ["The colonel hung his head..."] (6106), [circa 1877]
    - ["Come, circle, circle, round and round..."], poem (6107), undated (Box 27, Folder 644)
    - ["Come, here is adieu to the city..."], poem (6108), [1870?] (Box 27, Folder 645)
    - ["Come, my beloved, hear from me..."], poem (6109-6910), [1883?] (Box 27, Folder 646)
    - ["Come my little children..."], poem (6111), undated (Box 27, Folder 647)
    - ["Come then, my Henley, from our isle of rain..."], poem (3168), [1883?]
    - "Concerning Ligurra," poem (6114), undated
    - [Conversations in Writing], notes (6116-6119), 1884-1885 (Box 28, Folder 648-650)
    - "The Counterblast--1886," poem (6123-6124)
    - "The Counterblast Ironical" (6125-6126), 1881, 1886
    - "The Count's Secret" (6127), 1865 June 5
    - "Covenanters," notes (6128), [1873?] (Box 28, Folder 651)
    - "Cruelty to Animals" (6131), undated (Box 28, Folder 652)
    - "The Cruise of the Travelling Tub," table of contents (6132), undated
    - "Curaçoa," poem (6133), undated (Box 28, Folder 653)
    - "The Curse of De Vasco," poem (6134), 1863 (Box 28, Folder 654)
    - "Dapple and Rosinante," poem (6135), undated (Box 28, Folder 655)
    - "Dark Women," poem (6136-6138), undated (Box 28, Folder 656-657)
    - "The Daughter," poem (6139-6141), undated (Box 28, Folder 658)
    - "Davos in Winter" (copy) (6142), [1881?]
    - "Death," poem (6145), 1872 September 1
    - "Death in the Pot," table of contents (6146-6147), undated (Box 28, Folder 659)
    - [Diary, 1883] (6154) (Box 28, Folder 660)
    - ["Did ever mortal man hear tell of sae singular a ferlie..."], poem (6155), undated (Box 28, Folder 661)
    - ["Differences of country..."], essay (6156), undated (Box 28, Folder 662)
    - "Diogenes in London," fragment (8332), undated (Box 28, Folder 663)
    - "Ditty," poem (6158 and 8333), undated (Box 28, Folder 664-665)
    - "Doubts of the Poet Thamson," poem (2740), 1882 October 17
    - [Drawings Made in the Cévennes] (6165), 1878 (Box 28, Folder 666)
    - [Drinking] (6167), undated
    - "Droll Scene in Court: Pettigrew v. Johnstone" (6169), undated
    - "Dumyat" (6172), 1860 June 30 (Box 28, Folder 667)
    - [Dunoon. Encounter With a Fortune Teller, 1870] (6173) (Box 29, Folder 668)
    - [Dunoon. Visit in 1870 to a House Where R.L.S. Had Spent a Week in Childhood] (6174), undated (Box 29, Folder 669)
    - ["Ease the buttons where it galls you..."] (6178), undated (Box 29, Folder 670)
    - The Ebb-Tide (6179-6182), 1893 June 5, undated (Box 29, Folder 671-674)
    - "The Edifying Letters of the Rutherford Family" (6184-6185), undated
    - ["Eighty the years of his body..."], poem (6187), undated
    - "Embro Hie Kirk," poem (6188), undated (Box 29, Folder 675)
    - ["'Encl' breathed the rustic maid..."], poem (2760), 1883 October 3
    - ["'Encl' says he..."], poem (2760), 1883 October 3
    - "An English Breeze" (6192), [1880]
    - "The English in France," notes (6193), undated (Box 29, Folder 676)
    - "Epistle to Albert Dew-Smith" (6194), 1880 November (Box 29, Folder 677)
    - "Erotion's Epitaph (Epitaphium Erotii)" (6195), undated
    - "Escape at Bedtime," song (6196), undated
    - [Essays, projected], notes (6198), undated (Box 29, Folder 678)
    - "The Ethics of Crime," essay (6199), undated (Box 29, Folder 679)
    - "F.V. de G. S. Ave," poem (6203), 1885 May 19
    - [Fables, Etc. Agreement Between R.L.S. and Longmans, Green and Co.], contract (6204), 1895 September 3 (Box 29, Folder 680)
    - ["Fair isle at sea..."], poem (6207), undated
    - "Far Ballads and Songs of Travel", undated (Box 29, Folder 681)
      Includes:
      "Ditty" (6159)
      "In Memoriam" (6418)
      "To an Island Princess" (6991)
      "To Dr. Hake" (6997)
      [To Kalakua (With a Present of a Pearl] (7006)
      "To Mother MaryAnne" (7019)
      "To Princess Kaiulani" (7026)
      "To. S.C." (7029)
      "To the Muse" (7042)
      "The Vagabond" (7078)
      [A Voice From Home] (7087)
      "Wandering Willie" (7089)
      [We Have Loved Of Yore] (7101)
      "Winter" (7173)
      "To R.L.S." by Thomas Gordon Hake (7233)
    - ["Far have you come, my lady, from the town..."], poem (3275 and 6210), [1875 August], undated
    - ["Far sunken from the lurid glare of life..."], poem (6211), undated (Box 29, Folder 682)
    - ["Fairwell, fair day and fading light..."], poem (6213-6214), undated (Box 29, Folder 683)
    - "The Fat and the Lean," poem (3285), [circa 1885]
    - ["Fear not, dear friend, but freely live your days..."], poem (6217-6218), undated (Box 29, Folder 684)
    - "The Feast of Famine," poem (6219), undated (Box 29, Folder 685)
    - "Fighting the Ring" (6221), 1888 (Box 29, Folder 686)
    - "The Fish of the River," poem (6222), undated (Box 30, Folder 687)
    - ["Flower god, god of the spring..."], poem (6223), [1883?]
    - A Footnote to History (6224-6231), 1892, undated (Box 30, Folder 688-695)
    - ["For I have been warm with the..."], poem (6232), undated
    - "Forest Notes" (6238-6240), [circa 1875-1876] (Box 30, Folder 696)
    - [A Fragment in Memoriam] (6242-6243), 1872 (Box 30, Folder 697)
    - [A French Legend and Thoughts on Death] (6245), [circa 1875-1876]
    - [French Lesson for Austin Strong] (6246), undated (Box 30, Folder 698)
    - ["From Baildon..."] (6247), [1865] March 22
    - ["From the great seas, little and great return..."] (6248), [1883]
    - ["Gather ye roses while ye may..."] (6250), 1875 (Box 30, Folder 699)
    - ["Gem of my native hills..."] (3068), [1882 March?]
    - ["The giant bunker, great and grim..."] (6251), undated (Box 30, Folder 700)
    - "Go, Little Book–The Ancient Phrase" (6253-6254), undated (Box 30, Folder 701)
    - "The Go-Between" (5973, 6255-6256), 1893 (Box 30, Folder 702-704)
    - "God gave to me a child in part..." (6257), undated (Box 30, Folder 705)
    - "The Goldenson Mystery" (6260), undated
    - "A Good Boy," song (6261-6262), undated
    - "The Great North Road," notes and map (6265-6266), undated (Box 30, Folder 706)
    - "Grim Spirit of Finance," poem (2755), 1883 June 21
    - "Hail, Guest, and Enter Freely!" poem (6269), 1885 (Box 30, Folder 707)
    - ["Hail, rare apollo! And what thanks are due..."], poem (3124), [1886] July 12
    - "The Hair Trunk; or, the Ideal Commonwealth, an Extravaganza" (6271), [circa 1876]
    - "The Hanging Judge," playscript (6273-6274), undated (Box 30, Folder 708)
    - ["He pickled low, he pickled loud..."], poem (3566), [1886]
    - ["He that wins to laugh may choose..."], poem (6280), 1894 November (Box 30, Folder 709)
    - ["He was a man as debonair to view..."], poem (6281-6282), undated (Box 30, Folder 710)
    - "Health and Mountains" (copy) (6284), [1881?]
    - "Heathercat," notes and drafts (6287-6304), undated (Box 30, Folder 711-726)
    - ["Here by the old oak, beneath the pine..."], poem (6307-6308), undated
    - ["Here from the sea the unfruitful [?] sun shall rise..."], poem (6309), undated
    - ["Here lie the bones of R.L.S..."], poem (2906), [1888 January?]
    - ["Here lies Erotion..."], poem (6312), undated (Box 31, Folder 727)
    - ["Here, on this sheet of extra-superfine..."], poem (6313), 1882 September 5 (Box 31, Folder 728)
    - ["Here then I wake..."], poem (6314), undated (Box 31, Folder 729)
    - ["Here you rest among the vallies..."], poem (3273 and 6316), [1874?], undated
    - [Doctor Heskyn and Sickness in a Prison in Samoa] (6317), undated (Box 31, Folder 730)
    - "Hopes," poem (6318), 1872 August 2
    - "The House Beautiful," poem (6321), undated (Box 31, Folder 731)
    - "The House of Tembinoka," poem (6322-6323), undated (Box 31, Folder 732)
    - ["I am as good as deaf..."], poem (3285), [circa 1885-1886]
    - ["I did but see and pass..."], poem (6331), undated
    - ["I don't care for concealment..."] (6334), undated (Box 31, Folder 733)
    - ["I dreamed of forest alleys fair..."] (6336-6340), [circa 1870-1872]
    - ["I dreamed that I..."], poem (6341), undated
    - ["I fear not death tha comes to slay..."], poem (6343), undated
    - ["I find a point where I agree with Howells..."], poem (2920), [circa 1889 May]
    - ["I have a hoard of treasure in my breast..."], poem (6346-6347), 1870
    - ["I have loved these things with all my heart..."], poem (6349), undated
    - ["I know not how, but as I count..."], poem (6351), [1871]
    - ["I know not why I want to please..."], poem (6352), 1894 November (Box 31, Folder 734)
    - ["I love to be warm by the red fireside..."], poem (6355), undated
    - ["I now am a converted man..."], poem (3165), [1883?]
    - ["I read, dear friend, in your dear face..."], poem (3274), [circa 1874]
    - ["I saw red evening through the rain..."], poem (6360), [1875]
    - ["I sit up here at midnight..."], poem (6365), 1871 December
    - ["I smell the cliffs of England now..."], poem (6366), undated (Box 31, Folder 735)
    - ["I was in Eden once and with a star..."], poem (6370), [circa 1874-1875]
    - ["I who all the winter through..."], poem (6372), 1876 February
    - ["I will make you brooches..."], poem (6376-6378), undated
    - ["I will not tell but keep..."], poem (6379), undated (Box 31, Folder 736)
    - ["I will not tell, not I..."], poem (6380), undated
    - ["I would sing one song of a fair thing seen..."], poem (6382), undated
    - [Adelaide Ide's Diploma for French Lessons Given by R.L.S.] (6383), 1894 (Box 31, Folder 737)
    - ["If I could hate you, as I hate your love..."], poem (6385), [1876?]
    - ["If I had wings, my lady, like a dove..."], poem (6386), [1875]
    - [If I indeed have power to please..."], poem (6387-6388), undated
    - [If somewhere in the rainy far off seas..."], poem (6392), undated
    - "Ille Terrarum," poem (6398), undated (Box 31, Folder 738)
    - ["In a long lane formed by two files of half naked humanity..."], poem (6402), 1893 (Box 31, Folder 739)
    - ["In all the chimneys..."], poem (6403), undated
    - ["In autumn when the woods are red..."], poem (6405), [1875]
    - ["In dreams, unhappy, I behold you stand..."], poem (6406-6410), undated
    - ["In eighteen hundred and eighty three..."], poem (3522), [1883 February 1]
    - ["In every face I see the spring confest..."], poem (6411), undated
    - "In for a Penny" (6412), undated
    - "In Jacobum Casparis Et Sigrist Maler Epigrammata Octo," poem (6414-6417), undated (Box 31, Folder 740)
    - ["In part, the Johnsons both, and Dryden too..."], poem (6420), undated (Box 31, Folder 741)
    - ["In the green and gallant spring..."], poem (6423), 1875
    - "In the Highlands, In the Country Places," poem (6424), undated
    - In the South Seas (6426-6441), undated (Box 31, Folder 742-754)
    - In the South Seas (6442-6446), undated (Box 32, Folder 755-757)
    - [In the States] (6447), 1880 January
    - "The Indefatigable Schiff," poem (6448), undated
    - [Indenture] (6449), 1892 April 28
    - "Inscription for the Tankard of a Society Now Dissolved," poem (6456), 1873 (Box 32, Folder 758)
    - [Isabeau de Bavière, Queen of France], notes (6463), undated
    - "It is the Season Now to Go," poem (6467), undated (Box 32, Folder 759)
    - ["It's an excellent thing to speak, and yet it is good..."] (8342), undated
    - ["It's an owercome sooth for age an' youth..."], poem (6470), undated (Box 32, Folder 760)
    - ["It's forth across the roaring foam and towards the west..."], poem (6471), undated
    - "Jenkin, Professor Fleeming," obituary (6475), 1885 June 20 (Box 32, Folder 761)
    - "Katharine," poem (6477), undated (Box 32, Folder 762)
    - Kidnapped, [notes?] (6478-6480), undated
    - ["Know you the river near the grez..."], poem (6482), 1879 December
    - [Laafaele's Account With R.L.S.] (6483), 1892 February 2 (Box 32, Folder 763)
    - ["Lads of yore and lasses sang and glorified in singing..."], poem (6484), undated
    - "Lament of Aromaiterai," poem (6485), undated (Box 32, Folder 764)
    - ["Lang and I were dressed in our Sunday's best..."], poem (6489-6490), undated (Box 32, Folder 765)
    - ["Last night we had a thunderstorm in style..."], poem (6491), [1875]
    - "The Last of the Yeomen" (6492), undated
    - [Sir John Lauder of Fountainhall], notes (6495), undated
    - "The Laureat Ste'enson to the Thamson Class," poem (6496), [circa 1883-1884]
    - "Lay Morals" (6498-6499), undated (Box 32, Folder 766)
    - ["A lean and stiffened pantaloon..."], poem (6500), undated
    - [Leith, Water of], essay (6506), undated (Box 32, Folder 767)
    - "Lesson on the Sea," poem (6507), undated (Box 32, Folder 768)
    - ["Let him diviner vengeance take..."], poem (6508), undated
    - ["Let us come and join the clan of the Tevas..."], poem (6514), undated (Box 32, Folder 769)
    - [Letter. Imaginary Letter Signed] (6515-6516), 1885 March
    - [Letters Sent and Received by R.L.S.] (6517), 1892-[1894?] (Box 32, Folder 770)
    - "Life's Pantomime and Death's Transformation" (6518), undated
    - ["Light as my heart was long ago..."], poem (6519), [1875]
    - "The Light-Keeper," poem (6520), 1869 May (Box 32, Folder 771)
    - ["Like all our virtue..."], poem (6521), undated
    - ["Like an ingredient of the breathing air..."], poem (6522), undated (Box 32, Folder 772)
    - ["Like one who long has labored in a mine..."], poem (6523), undated
    - "Lines To Be Sent With the Present of a Sketch Book" (6525-6526), 1870
    - [List of Books] (6528-6529), [1880], undated
    - [List of Subjects of Possible Articles or Stories], notes (6530), undated (Box 32, Folder 773)
    - [List of Titles of Poems by R.L.S. and Others] (6531), undated (Box 32, Folder 774)
    - ["A little before me and hark!"], poem (6534), undated
    - "Little Odes", 1872 (Box 32, Folder 775)
      ["O South, South, South! O happy land!"] (6664)
      ["The relic taken, what avails the shrine?"] (6786)
      ["The gloomy northern day..."] (6971)
      ["Though deep indifference should drowse..."] (6980)
      ["Though he, that ever kind and true..."]
      "To Minnie, With a Hand-Glass" (7015)
      "To Sydney" (7032)
    - ["Lo, now, my guest..."], poem (6539), 1885 (Box 32, Folder 776)
    - ["Long time I lay in little ease..."], poem (6542-6543), [1882]
    - ["Loud and low in the chimney..."], poem (6545), [circa 1883]
    - ["Love is the very heart of spring..."], poem (6546), 1876 (Box 32, Folder 777)
    - ["Love, what is love?"], poem (6547-6548), 1876, undated
    - "A Lowden Sabbath Morn," poem (6551-6552), 1886, undated
    - ["A lytle jape of Tusherie..."], poem (3167), [1883 May]
    - ["Madame, vous pas oublié le coffee-pot..."] (6555), undated (Box 32, Folder 778)
    - "A Malaga in Samoa" (6556), [1899-1900] (Box 32, Folder 779)
    - "Malaga in Tutuila", undated
    - ["Man sails in the deep awhile..."] (6557), 1879 February
    - "Mahiki," notes (6558), [1890?] (Box 32, Folder 780)
    - "A Martial Elegy for Some Lead Soldiers" (6561), [1882] (Box 32, Folder 781)
    - The Master of Ballantrae (6563-6564), undated (Box 32, Folder 782)
    - "The Master of the House Tusitala," poem (6566), undated (Box 32, Folder 783)
    - "Mater Triumphans," poem (6569), undated (Box 32, Folder 784)
    - "Matthew Daventry" (6572), undated (Box 33, Folder 785)
    - [Memoirs of Himself] (6573), 1873 May 18 (Box 33, Folder 786)
    - Memories & Portraits, preface (6574), 1887, undated (Box 33, Folder 787)
      Includes letters from Robert Louis Stevenson to Chatto & Windus (7947-7949)
    - ["Men are Heaven's piers..."], poem (6575), undated
    - ["Methought that I walked in spirit choosing my grave..."], poem (6578), undated (Box 33, Folder 788)
    - ["A mile an' a bittock..."], poem (6579-6580), [1883 or 1884?] (Box 33, Folder 789-790)
    - "The Mill-House," poems (6581), 1866 (Box 33, Folder 791)
    - "The Mirror Speaks," poem (6583), 1886 March (Box 33, Folder 792)
    - "The Misgivings of Convalescence" (6585), 1881 March 17 (Box 33, Folder 793)
    - "Monmouth," play and dedication (6587 and 3551), 1868 September 6 (Box 33, Folder 794-795)
    - ["A monody... On the death of Mr. Pogue O'Nelle..."], poem (3322), [1868 September 12]
    - "Monte Carlo" (6588), undated (Box 33, Folder 796)
    - [Monterey, California], notes (6589), 1879 (Box 33, Folder 797)
    - "Moral Tales" (6591), undated (Box 33, Folder 798)
    - "Mother and Daughter," poem (6595), undated (Box 33, Folder 799)
    - "A Mountain Town in France" (6597), undated (Box 33, Folder 800)
    - [Musical Compositions] (6599), undated (Box 33, Folder 801-804)
    - ["My body which my dungeon is..."], poem (6600), undated (Box 34, Folder 805)
    - [My Book], poem (6601), undated (Box 34, Folder 806)
    - "My Conscience!" poem (6602), undated (Box 34, Folder 807)
    - ["My heart, when the first blackbird sings..."], poem (6604-6605), 1871
    - ["My house, I say..."], poem (6606-6607), undated (Box 34, Folder 808-809)